A Guide to the Records of the Secretary of Administration, 1978-1989
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Records of the Office of the Secretary of Transportation, 1978-1989
The Library of Virginia
33750
13 cu. ft. (13 boxes)
Office of the Secretary of Transportation
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Accession 33750 was transfered from the Office of the Secretary of Administration, on 17 May 1990, to the Virginia State Library and Archives for permanent retention.
Biographical Information
The Office of Administration was established in 1966 as part of the Office of the Governor to assist the chief executive in carrying out his duties. Several agencies including the divisions of the Budget, Personnel, Engineering and Building and Planning reported to the Commissioner of Administration. This system was inadequate. In 1970, the Governor's Management Commission Study recommended the creation of six "Deputy Governors" to assist the Chief Executive in his managerial duties. Compatible functions of government were grouped under these administrative heads, who would serve as the Governors top management team or "secretariats," as they are called now.
Governor Linwood Holton's top priority for the 1972 session of the General Assembly was a proposal for a Governor's Cabinet, reorganizing state agencies into six major departments--each headed by a secretary appointed by the governor. The Office of Administration was made one of these six departments. The office of Secretary of Administration was created on April 8, 1972, by an act passed by the General Assembly. Governor Holton appointed T. Edward Temple, the Commissioner of Administration since 1970, as the first Secretary of Administration. When Temple took office on July 1, 1972, he was responsible for the divisions of the Budget, Personnel, Engineering and Buildings, Automated Data Processing, Justice and Crime Prevention, State Planning and Community Affairs, Council on the Environment, State Board of Elections and the Office of Special Programs. The Office has undergone a series of administrative reorganizations since 1972. On April 12, 1976, the Legislature combined the secretariats for administration and finance, effective July 1, 1976. On July 1, 1984, the offices were separated. The Secretary of Administration is a member of the Governor's Cabinet, and is appointed by the governor, subject to confirmation by the General Assembly. Currently, the Secretary of Administration is responsible for the direction or jurisdiction over the following state agencies and boards: Department of Charitable Gaming, Compensation Board, State Board of Elections, Department of Employment Dispute Resolution, Department of General Services, Department of Human Resource Management, Council on Human Rights, Public Broadcasting Board, and the Department of Veterans Services.
T. Edward Temple, the first Secretary of Administration, announced in August 1973 that he was leaving state service effective January 1974. In December 1973, Governor-elect Mills E. Godwin, Jr., announced the appointment of Maurice B. Rowe, III, as Secretary of Administration. Rowe had served as Secretary of Commerce and Resources in the Holton administration. On July 1, 1976, the secretariates of administration and finance were combined. Rowe served until the end of the Godwin administration in January 1978 when he became Secretary of Commerce and Resources in the Dalton administration. In December 1977 Governor-elect John N. Dalton picked Charles B. Walker, the state comptroller, as Secretary of Administration and Finance. The office wielded great influence and authority under Walker who was known as the "Little Governor". Walker resigned in June 1981 to become a vice-president for Ethyl Corporation. Stuary Connock, state budget and planning director, served as Secretary of Administration and Finance until the end of Dalton's term in January 1982.
Governor-elect Charles S. Robb, the first Democrat to be elected governor since 1965, did not retain any of Dalton's cabinet secretaries. Robb appointed Wayne F. Anderson, a former Alexandria city manager, Secretary of Administration and Finance. Anderson announced his resignation in May 1984 to join the faculty of George Mason University. His resignation was prompted by a cabinet reorganization to take effect on July 1, 1984 which divided the Secretary of Administration and Finance into separate secretariats and combined the secretariats of transportation and public safety. Governor Robb appointed Secretary of Transportation Andrew B. Fogarty as new Secretary of Administration. Fogarty served until June 1985 when he became Sectretary of Transportation and Public Safety following the resignation of Franklin E. White. David K. McCloud, Robb's chief of staff, assumed the duties of Secretary of Administration for the remainder of Robb's term.
In December 1985, Governor-elect Gerald L. Baliles chose Carolyn J. Moss, head of the Office of Minority Business Enterprise under Governor Robb, as Secretary of Administration. Moss served until the end of Baliles' term in 1990. Governor-elect L. Douglas Wilder appointed Ruby G. Martin, a Richmond attorney, as Secretary of Administration. In January 1994 Governor-elect George Allen, the first Republican elected governor since 1977, appointed his campaign manager, Michael E. Thomas, Secretary of Administration. Thomas served until the end of Allen's term in January 1998. Governor James S. Gilmore appointed Thomas Deputy Secretary of Technology in August 1998. In January 1998 Governor-elect James S. Gilmore III named G. Bryan Slater as Secretary of Administration. Slater also served as Gilmore's Deputy Chief of Staff. He worked on Gilmore's campaign for attorney general in 1993 and served as his director of administration when Gilmore was Virginia Attorney General (1994-1997). Slater resigned in March 2001 to work for the Republican National Committee which Gilmore chaired. He was replaced by his deputy, Donald L. Moseley who served until the end of the Gilmore administration in January 2002.
Governor-elect Mark R. Warner selected Sandra Bowen as Secretary of Administration in January 2002. Bowen had previously served as Special Assistant to Governor Charles S. Robb, and as Secretary of the Commonwealth during the administration of Governor Gerald L. Baliles. She was also the Director of Gubernatorial Transition between the Robb and Baliles administrations. Secretary Bowen served under Governor Warner for his entire term, and was replaced in 2006 when Governor-elect Timothy Kaine selected Viola Baskerville as his Secretary of Administration.
Scope and Content
This collection contains both incomming and out going correspondence, reports, memoranda, notes, publications, budget documents and related materials.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I. Correspondence and Subject Files
Contents List
- Series I. Correspondence and Subjects Files, 1978-1989., Extent: 13. (Box 1-13)
  This collection maintains the arragement created by the creating organization.
  - Department of Personnel and Training: Audit/Financial, 1985-1986. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Department of Personnel and Training: Budget, 1987. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Department of Personnel and Training: Salary Survey Reports, 1986. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Department of Personnel and Training: Wage Employee Project, 1984-1986. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Department of Personnel and Training: Health Benefits, 1985-1987. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Department of Personnel and Training: Equal Employment Opportunity/AA Office, 1985-1986. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Department of Personnel and Training: Virginia Equal Employment Opportunity Council, 1986. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Department of General Services: Asbestos 1 of 2, 1986. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Department of General Services: Asbestos 2 of 2, 1986. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Department of General Services: Asbestos, 1987. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Department of Information Technology: General, 1985. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Department of Information Technology: Office Automation Plan, 1985-1986. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Rural Virginia Developement Foundation, 1985-1986. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Virginia Port Authority, 1985. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Compensation Board, 1985. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Virginia Supplimental Retirement System: Executive Agreement, 1985. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Virginia Supplimental Retirement System: Deferred Compensation Plan, 1985-1987. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Virginia Supplimental Retirement System: Disability, 1985. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Virginia Supplimental Retirement System: General, 1984-1985. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Council, Human Rights, 1987. (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Secretary of the Commonwealth, 1986. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Ray's Landfill, 1984-1988. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Small Business Administration, 1984-1988. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Governor's Office Issues, 1984-1988. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Campaign Promises, 1984-1988. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Governor's Retreat, Fall, 1987. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Survey - Governor's Retreat, 1987. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Cabinet Retreat Action Plans, 1987 Apr 14. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Cabinet Retreat, 1987 June 30. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Time Study, 1987. (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Governor's Cabinet Retreat, 1987 Mar 13. (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Agency Head Retreat, 1986 Oct 8-10. (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Memoranda to and from the Governor's Office, 1987. (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Memoranda to and from the Governor's Office - Andy Fogarty, 1987. (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Governor's Fellows Program, 1988. (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Governor's Fellows Program, 1989. (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Meeting with Governor Dooley (RE: General Services), 1986. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Department of General Services: General, 1985-1987. (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Department of General Services: Executive Agreement, 1985-1987. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Department of General Services: Capital Outlay, 1984-1985. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Department of General Services: Purchase and Supply, 1983. (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Department of General Services: Risk Management, 1985. (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Department of General Services: Engineering, 1985. (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Department of General Services: Negligence Insurance, 1978-1985. (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Secretary of Administration: Memoranda to Agencies, 1985-1986. (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Secretary of Administration: Budget, 1986-1988. (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Secretary of Administration: Affirmative Action, 1985. (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Secretary of Administration: Overview, 1978-1989. (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Secretary of Administration: Briefing Papers, 1986. (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Secretary to the Cabinet, 1987. (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Cabinet Work Sessions, 1986. (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Executive Agreement: Department of Information Technology, 1985-1986. (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Virginia Employment Commission Memoranda, 1985-1986. (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Governor's Roanoke Trip, 1985-1986. (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Meeting - McGee, 1986 Apr 29. (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Administrative Decentralization in Higher Education, 1985-1986. (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Office of Minority Business Enterprise Memoranda, 1982. (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Budget Follow-Up, 1985-1986. (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Social Services Block Grant - House Bill 1446, 1985-1986. (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Combined Charitable Campaign: Meeting, 1989. (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Combined Charitable Campaign: Guidelines, 1989. (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Combined Charitable Campaign: Appeals, 1989. (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Combined Charitable Campaign: Evaluation, 1989. (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - United Way/CVS, 1988-1989. (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Comptroller's Office, 1985-1986. (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Board of Elections, 1984-1985. (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Nomenclature, 1986. (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Jobs for American Graduates, 1982-1985. (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Judicial Retirement, 1985. (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Southwestern Virginia Hospital, 1985. (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Education/Tuition and Fees, 1983. (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Hazardous Waste Facility - Sitting Board, 1986-1988. (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Department of General Services: Budget and General, 1984-1987. (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - State Penitentiary, 1984-1988. (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - State Penitentiary, 1984-1988. (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - John T. Hazel, 1987 Apr 16. (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - State Penitentiary Task Force, 1984-1988. (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - State Penitentiary Sale, 1984-1988. (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Intellectual Property Policy: Mines, Minerals and Energy, 1984-1988. (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Intellectual Property Policy: Mines, Minerals and Energy, 1984-1988. (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Intellectual Property Policy: Virginia State Library and Archives, 1984-1988. (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Intellectual Property Policy: Steel Erectors Association of America, 1984-1988. (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Intellectual Property Policy: Virginia Port Authority, 1984-1988. (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Intellectual Property Policy: State Police, 1984-1988. (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Board of Elections, 1984-1988. (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Air Polution Control Board, 1984-1988. (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Virginia Employment Commission, 1984-1988. (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Virginia Science Museum, 1984-1988. (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Department o Education, 1984-1988. (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Intellectual Property - General and Policy, 1984-1988. (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Department of Information Technology, 1984-1988. (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Rights for the Disabled, 1984-1988. (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Deaf and Hard of Hearing, 1984-1988. (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Virginia Museum of Fine Arts, 1984-1988. (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Mental Health, Mental Retardation, Substance Abuse Services, 1984-1988. (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Emergency Services, 1984-1988. (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Correctional Education, 1984-1988. (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Intellectual Property Policy: Department of Transportation, 1984-1988. (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Department of Transportation: Intellectual Property, 1984-1988. (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Combined Charitable Campaign, Revision of Procedure, 1985-1988. (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Combined Charitable Campaign, Revision of Procedure, 1985-1988. (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - United Way, 1985-1987. (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Department of General Services: Bureau of Chemistry - Intellectual Property Policy, 1985-1988. (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Department of General Services: Intellectually Property Policy, 1985-1988. (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Local Government - General, 1985. (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Commission of Local Government, 1981-1985. (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Commission of Local Government, 1981-1985. (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Department of Employee Relations Counselors, 1985. (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Department of Planning and Budget: General, 1985. (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Department of Planning and Budget: Salary Facilities, 1985. (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Magnetic Tape - Virginia Port Authority, 1985-1988. (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - "Assisting the Beginning Teacher", 1985-1988. (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - "Beginning Teaching Handbook", 1985-1988. (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - State Library, 1985-1988. (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Virginia Museum of Fine Arts, 1985-1988. (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Deaf and Hard of Hearing, 1985-1988. (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Jamestown/Yorktown Foundation, 1985-1988. (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Department of Information Technology, 1985-1988. (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Intellectual Property Policy System - Phase 1, 1987. (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Virginia Port Authority, 1985-1988. (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Department of Medical Assistance Services, 1985-1988. (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Star of Bethlehem, 1985-1988. (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Forms, 1985-1988. (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Copyright, 1987, Commonwealth of Virginia, 1985-1988. (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - 5 1/4 Floppy Disk Case (10 Disks), 1985-1988. (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - VHS - "Take a Good Look" Fake ID's, 1985-1988. (Box 13, Folder 16)
  - Helping Students Learn (HP Data Cartridge), 1985-1988. (Box 13, Folder 17)
  - Virginia Port Authority Computer System Software, 1987. (Box 13, Folder 18)
  - Department of Rehab Services, 1985-1988. (Box 13, Folder 19)
  - Department of State Policy, 1985-1988. (Box 13, Folder 20)
  - Intellectual Property Policy - Position, 1985-1988. (Box 13, Folder 21)
  - Intellectual Property Policy, 1985-1988. (Box 13, Folder 22)
  - Software, 1985-1988. (Box 13, Folder 23)
  - Governor's Cabinet Photograph: Godwin and Dalton, 1978-1982. (Box 13, Folder 24)